H. Corwin Hinshaw Papers 1925-1994 Mss.Ms.Coll.107
American Philosophical Society
- Series II. Streptomycin Research, 1939-1945; 2 boxes, 1 lin. foot
  - Contemplated Streptomycin Studies in Tuberculosis Therapy, n.d.; Feldman, William Hugh, 1892-1974 (Box 2)
  - "Inhibition of the growth of various bacteria and fungi by streptomycin", Heilman, Fordyce (Box 2)
  - "The Use of Fleming's Modification of the Wright Slide Cell Technic for Determining Streptomycin in Body Fluids", n.d.; Herrell, Wallace E. (Box 2)
  - "Human Pharmacology: Absorption and Exceretion in Man", Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 2)
  - "Tuberculosis", n.d.; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 2)
  - Extract from Minutes, n.d.; Mayo Laboratory and Research Committee. (Box 2)
  - "Statement Concerning the Significance of the Contribution of William H. Feldman and H. Corwin Hinshaw to Chemotherapy in Tuberculosis", Mayo Laboratory and Research Committee. (Box 2)
  - Streptomycin Research - Tables and Charts (nineteen), Mayo Laboratory and Research Committee. (Box 2)
  - 1945-1946, Reports on Streptomycin Treatment:.
    - Patient One, 1945
    - Patient Two, 1945
    - Patient Three, 1945
    - Patient Four, 1945
    - Patient Five, 1945
    - Patient Six, 1945
    - Patient Seven, 1945
    - Patient Eight, 1945
    - Patient Nine, 1945
    - Patient Ten, 1945
    - Patient Eleven, 1946
    - Patient Twelve, 1946
    - Patient Thirteen, 1946
    - Patient Fourteen, 1946
    - Patient Fifteen, 1946
    - Patient Sixteen, 1946
- Series III. Printed Materials, 1926-1990; 1.5 boxes, 0.75 lin. feet
  Includes published articles from medical and scientific research journals, clippings from newspapers and popular periodicals, and pamphlets and information booklets produced by pharmaceutical companies or tuberculosis societies. Series III is arranged chronologically. The earliest articles reflect Hinshaw's work on protozoology, and there is one paper concerning his work on medical problems in high-altitude aviation. The bulk of the items, however, concern streptomycin and chemotherapy for tuberculosis.
  Contributors in Series III include:
  Birath, Gösta
  Budgie, Elizabeth
  Courmont, Paul
  Feldman, William H[ugh], 1892-1974
  Moses, Harold E.
  Parr, Leland W.
  Pfuetze, Karl H.
  Schatz, Albert, 1920
  Youmans, Guy Parry, 1908-
  - Correlation of Protozoan Infections of Human Mouth with Extent of Certain Lesions in Pyorrhea Alveolaris, 1926; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 3)
  - On the Morphology and Mitosis of Trichomonas Buccalis (Goodey) Kofoid, 1926; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 3)
  - Cultivation of Trichomonas Buccalis: A Protozoan of the Human Mouth, 1927; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 3)
  - Experimental Infection of Dogs with Endamoeba Gingivalis and Trichomonas Buccalis of Human Mouth, 1928; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 3)
  - Diagnostic Standards and Classification of Tuberculosis, 1940 (Box 3)
  - Theraputics, 1 February 1941 (Box 3)
  - Medical Problems in Aviation, 2 May 1941; HCH and Boothby, Walter M. (Box 3)
  - Treatment of Experimental Tuberculosis, 27 September 1941; Feldman, William Hugh, 1892-1974 (Box 3)
  - Promin in the Treatment of Tuberculosis, June 1942; Moses, Harold E. (Box 3)
  - Chemotherapy in Tuberculosis - An Appraisal of Present Evidence and of Future Possibilities, December 1942; Mann, Frank C. (Box 3)
  - Observations on the Use of Promin (Sodium P, P1-Diaminodiphenylsulfone-N, N1-Didextrose Sulfonate) in Clinical Tuberculosis: A Progress Report, 1942; Feldman, William Hugh, 1892-1974 (Box 3)
  - Tuberculochemotherapy, April 1943; Feldman, William Hugh, 1892-1974 (Box 3)
  - Factors in Resistance to Tuberculosis as Revealed by a Case-Finding Program, April 1943; Parr, Leland W. (Box 3)
  - Some Toxicological Bacteriological, and Pharmacological Properties of Antimicrobial Agents Produced by Soil Micro-Organisms, May 1943; Robinson, Harry John (Box 3)
  - New Sulphur Drug Aids in Tuberculosis, 15 October 1943 (Box 3)
  - Use of New Tuberculosis Drug to Be Discussed at Seal Session, 28 October 1943 (Box 3)
  - Mass Examination Plan Instead of Drugs Urged by Researcher to Fight Tuberculosis, October 1943 (Box 3)
  - The Promin Treatment of Leprosy. A Progress Report, 26 November 1943; Faget, G. H. et al. (Box 3)
  - The Effects on Experimental Tuberculosis of 4, 4'-Diaminodiphenylsulfone, March 1944; Moses, Harold E. (Box 3)
  - Aspects of Epidemiology of Tuberculosis, 15 June 1944; Parr, Leland W. (Box 3)
  - Chemotherapy of Clinical Tuberculosis with Promin P, P'-Diaminodiphenylsulfone-N, N'-Didextrose Sulfonate: A Second Progress Report, July 1944; Feldman, William Hugh, 1892-1974 (Box 3)
  - Isolation of Antibiotic Substances from Soil Micro-Organisms, with Special Reference to Streptothricin and Streptomycin, 15 November 1944; Budgie, Elizabeth (Box 3)
  - Chemotherapy of Tuberculosis, 1944; Feldman, William Hugh, 1892-1974 (Box 3)
  - Chemotherapeutic Properties of Streptomycin, 1944; Smith, Dorothy G. (Box 3)
  - Streptomycin, a Substance Exhibiting Antibiotic Activity Against Gram-Positive and Gram-Negative Bacteria, 1944; Budgie, Elizabeth (Box 3)
  - Streptomycin Effective as Weapon Against Tuberculosis in Guinea Pigs, 15 January 1945 (Box 3)
  - Promin in Leprosy, February 1945July 1946 (Box 3)
  - State Urged to Unite Agencies for Stronger Fight Against Disease, 3 May 1945; Douglass, Ellwood (Box 3)
  - Streptomycin for Typhoid: A Pharmacologic Study, 19 May 1945; Reimann, Hobart A. (Box 3)
  - Penicillin's Sister, 3 September 1945 (Box 3)
  - Streptomycin in Treatment of Clinical Tuberculosis: A Preliminary Report, 5 September 1945; Feldman, William Hugh, 1892-1974 (Box 3)
  - Specialists Warn Public Drugs for T.B. Unproven, 22 October 1945 (Box 3)
  - Chemotherapy in Tuberculosis, October 1945; Feldman, William Hugh, 1892-1974 (Box 3)
  - A Review...Streptomycin, November 1945; Waksman, Selman A., (Selman Abraham), 1888-1973 (Box 3)
  - Streptomycin, 4 February 1946 (Box 3)
  - Increase in Resistance of Tubercle Bacilli to Streptomycin: A Preliminary Report, 20 March 1946; Youmans, Guy P. (Box 3)
  - Treatment of Tuberculosis of the Larynx with Streptomycin: Report of Case, March 1946 (Box 3)
  - Streptomycin, 21 May 1946 (Box 3)
  - Relation of Dosage to Streptomycin Toxicity, 22 May 1946; Tompsett, Ralph (Box 3)
  - Streptomycin may turn out to be...., 24 June 1946; Stafford, Jane (Box 3)
  - New Drug's Affect on TB Is Minimized, July 1946; *Case, Bill (Box 3)
  - Promising Drug, 10 September 1946 (Box 3)
  - The Chemotherapy of Tuberculosis, September 1946; Feldman, William Hugh, 1892-1974 (Box 3)
  - Streptomycin Valuable as Stopgap in TB Treatment, 30 November 1946 (Box 3)
  - Streptomycin in Treatment of Clinical Tuberculosis, 1946; Pfuetze, Karl H. (Box 3)
  - Treatment of Tuberculosis with Streptomycin, 1946; Pfuetze, Karl H. (Box 3)
  - Action des substances antibiotiques sur le bacille de Koch en cultures homogènes, 8 February 1947; Morel, A. (Box 3)
  - The Story of Streptomycin, April 1947 (Box 3)
  - Action antibiotique de la pénicilline sur les cultures troubles homogènes du Bacille de Koch S.A., P.C., April 1947; Gardère, Henri (Box 3)
  - "L'application de streptomycine en Belgique" and "Note préliminaire sur les observations recueillies au cours d'un essai de traitement de la méningite tuberculeuse par la streptomycine", April 1947; Gratia, André (Box 3)
  - The Antibacteria Approach to the Treatment of Tuberculosis, 10 May 1947; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 3)
  - NAPT Bulletin, June 1947 (Box 3)
  - Conditions d'action de la pénicilline in vitro sur le Bacille de Koch, July 1947; Gardère, Henri (Box 3)
  - The College of Idaho Bulletin, October 1947 (Box 3)
  - Pulmonary Emphysema and Tuberculosis, November 1947; Guggenheim, Albert (Box 3)
  - Streptomycin in Ophthalmology, November 1947; Bellows, John G. (Box 3)
  - Recent Advances in Pulmonary Diseases, 4 December 1947; Smart, Reginald H. (Box 3)
  - Streptomycin in 1947 (Box 3)
  - Drug Aiding Fight on Tuberculosis, June 1948 (Box 3)
  - Action de la Pénicilline sur le Bacille de Koch et sur la Tuberculose, August 1948; Courmont, Paul (Box 3)
  - La terapia con streptomicina nella tubercolosi polmonare ed extra-polmonare, August 1948; Carpi, Umberto (Box 3)
  - Streptomycin in the Treatment of Tuberculosis, 4 September 1948; Amberson, J. Burns (Box 3)
  - Streptomycin: An Antibiotic Agent Effective Against Experimental and Clinical Tuberc., October 1948; Feldman, William Hugh, 1892-1974 (Box 3)
  - Prevention of Tuberculosis Among Students of Medicine, November 1948; Diehl, Harold S. et al. (Box 3)
  - Management of Idiopathic Pleural Effusion, November 1948; Howson, Carl R. (Box 3)
  - Dihydrostreptomycin: Its Effect on Experimental Tuberculosis, November 1948; Karlson, Alfred G. (Box 3)
  - Rest in the Treatment of Tuberculosis, 1948?; Hayes, Edward W. (Box 3)
  - The Clinical Administration of Dihydostreptomycin (sic) in Tuberculosis, 1948?; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 3)
  - Dihydrostreptomycin Squibb, April 1952 (Box 3)
  - Streptomycin Bibliography, August 1952 (Box 3)
  - TB Drugs - Premature, July 1954 (Box 3)
  - Antimicrobial Therapy of Tuberculosis in 1952, May 1955; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 3)
  - Historical Notes on Earliest Use of Streptomycin in Clinical Tuberculosis, 28 May 1957; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 3)
  - The First Clinical Trial of Streptomycin in Human Tuberculosis, September 1958; Pfuetze, Karl H. (Box 3)
  - U.S.S.R. Invited Dr. H.C. Hinshaw to Conference, December 1958 (Box 3)
  - Speculations on the Future treatment and Control of Tuberculosis, 28 May 1960; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 3)
  - The Award of the Trudau medal for 1958, 21 November 1960 (Box 3)
  - Council on Drugs - excerpt, October 1963 (Box 3)
  - Dr. Hallenbeck leaving Clinic, 5 October 1963 (Box 3)
  - Tuberculosis, June 1964; Feldman, William Hugh, 1892-1974 (Box 3)
  - Auditory Ototoxicity in Tuberculosis Patients Treated with Dihydrostreptomycin, October 1965; Heck, Walter E. (Box 3)
  - Streptomycin 1944-1964, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Antibiotics and Dentistry - Part I, January 1968; Schatz, Albert (Box 3)
  - Nonsmokers and the Geographic Pathology of Lung Cancer, 11 May 1968; Kreyberg, Leiv (Box 3)
  - Leprosy and Tuberculosis, 1969; Long, Esmond R., (Esmond Ray), 1890- (Box 3)
  - Grim Warning to City On Loss of TB Clinics, 1969; Anspacher, Carolyn (Box 3)
  - Introduction of Para-amino-salicylic Acid and Streptomycin in the Treatment of Tuberculosis, 1969; Birath, Gösta (Box 3)
  - Tuberculosis Chemotherapy: Reminiscence of In Vivo Research, April 1982; Feldman, William Hugh, 1892-1974 (Box 3)
  - Tuberculosis Chemotherapy: Reminiscences of Early Clinical Trials, 10 December 1987; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 3)
  - The Dawn of Chemotherapy of Tuberculosis, 15 May 1989; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 3)
  - 50 Years Ago (1937), 25 September 1989 (Box 3)
  - The White Plague: Down and Out, or Up and Coming?, 23 May 1990; Murray, John F. (Box 3)
  - 25th Anniversary of 1st Streptomycin Use on Humans Nears in Cannon Falls, n.d.; Severson, Harold (Box 3)
  - Mayo Clinic Honors Dr. Corwin Hinshaw, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Dr. Feldman is Honored, n.d. (Box 3)
  - I never asked for this!, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Pulmonary Tuberculosis: A Journey down the Centuries - excerpts, n.d.; Keers, R.Y. (Box 3)
  - Profile: Louis Levin, M.D., n.d. (Box 3)
  - Are You Afraid of Tuberculosis?, n.d.; Stocker, J.A. (Box 3)
  - Streptomycin Merck, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Streptomycin Therapy, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Streptomycin, which is derived from... (Box 3)
  - The Patient Gets Up, Trimble, Harold Guyon (Box 3)
- Series IV. Miscellaneous materials, 1925-1991; 1 box, 0.5 lin. feet
  Materials in this series fall into four discreet groups. The first, "Autobiographical Notes," is made up of autobiographical writings by Hinshaw, most of which seem to be preparations for a memoir which was never completed. It is arranged alphabetically by subject. The second group, "Early Research," focuses on Hinshaw's early work in protozoology, including his Ph.D. thesis and associated research notes and writings. It is arranged alphabetically by title or subject. The third group, "Miscellaneous" contains miscellaneous notes and manuscripts. They are also arranged alphabetically by title or subject. "World Travel," the fourth group, contains copies of papers presented and other materials associated with his international travel for professional purposes: the 1953 "World Tour" to Europe and Asia, the 1955 trip to Argentina for the V Congreso Argentino de Tisiología, the 1957 trip to Moscow for the Sixth All Union Congress on Tuberculosis, and the 1959 short course on Chest Disease he taught in New Zealand. Although some of the material in this group does relate to tuberculosis and streptomycin, it is housed here rather than in Series II because it is informational and interpretive rather than original research. The material in "World Travel" is arranged chronologically. At the end of this series, there is the draft of Marjorie Pyle's book The Good Fight, arranged in chapter order.
  - Autobiographical Notes - Biographical sketch, n.d.; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 5)
  - Autobiographical Notes - Contributions - Chapters in other volumes (bibliography), n.d.; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 5)
  - Autobiographical Notes - CV, [1980s?]; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 5)
  - Autobiographical Notes - Forward, n.d.; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 5)
  - Autobiographical Notes - Garland, Henry L., Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 5)
  - Autobiographical Notes - Jinnah, 7 January 1991; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 5)
  - Autobiographical Notes - Jinnah: "Lady Mountbatten - Nehru's Lover", 26 August 1980; *HCH (Box 5)
  - Autobiographical Notes - Lung Associations, n.d.; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 5)
  - Autobiographical Notes - Miscellaneous, n.d.; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 5)
  - Autobiographical Notes - Mudd, Stuart, n.d.; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 5)
  - Autobiographical Notes - "Soong Ching-ling dies...", n.d.; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 5)
  - Autobiographical Notes - Tuberculosis, n.d.; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 5)
  - Autobiographical Notes - Waksman, 3 January 1991; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 5)
  - Autobiographical Notes - Who's Who in America profile, n.d.; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 5)
  - Early Research - The Amobea of the Mouth in Relation to Incidence of Pyorrhea, Clinical Symptoms, Extent of Lesions, and Age of Patients, HCH Simonton, F. Vance (Box 5)
  - Early Research - Miscellaneous notes relating to dentistry/pyorrhea, n.d.; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 5)
  - Early Research - Notes on Canine Research, n.d.; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 5)
  - Early Research - Programme of the final Public Examination for the Degree of Doctor of Philosophy of Horton Corwin Hinshaw - University of California, 20 April 1927 (Box 5)
  - Early Research - The Protozoa of the Human Mouth - Experimental Record, 1925-1927; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 5)
  - Early Research - The Protozoa of the Human Mouth - Ph.D. thesis (missing pages 5-56), [1927]; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 5)
  - Early Research - Protozoa plates, [1927?]; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 5)
  - Early Research - Protozoology - Class notes, n.d.; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 5)
  - Early Research - Protozoology - Laboratory drawings, n.d.; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 5)
  - Early Research - Tentative Outline for Ph.D. thesis, n.d.; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 5)
  - Early Research - Untitled [Paper on Gingivitis], n.d.; Kofoid, C.A. HCH (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous, Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous - A Doctor Looks at the Pharmaceutical Industry, Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous - Mayo Foundation Distinguished Alumnus Award - Itinerary, 12 April 1990 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous - Note about earliest Charts and Case Histories, 21 November 1970; *HCH (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous - Note concerning reprints, n.d.; *HCH (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous - The Physician as an Expert Witness in Legal Disputes Regarding Occupational Lung Disease, 4 October 1973; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous - Pilot's license, 2 September 1947; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous - Remarks on Presentation of the 1957 Medal of the American College of Chest Physicians to Dr. William Feldman, Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 5)
  - World Travel - Present Day Trends in Antibacterial Drug Therapy of Tuberculosis - 1953 World Lecture Tour, Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 5)
  - World Travel - Report of lecture Tour to European and Asiatic Countries - 1953 World Lecture Tour, Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 5)
  - World Travel - Informal remarks/List of Participants - V Congreso Argentino de Tisiología, November 1955 (Box 5)
  - World Travel - Roundtable Discussion Questions - V Congreso Argentino de Tisiología, November 1955 (Box 5)
  - World Travel - Specific Drug Therapy in Tuberculosis: An Analysis of Current Trends -- V Congreso Argentino de Tisiología, November 1955; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 5)
  - World Travel - Moscow Itinerary, [1957] (Box 5)
  - World Travel - Present Day Treatment of Tuberculosis in the U.S.A. - Sixth All Union Congress on Tuberculosis, June 1957; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 5)
  - World Travel - New Zealand Medical Registration, 13 March 1959 (Box 5)
  - World Travel - Course in Chest Disease, 16-26 March 1959; Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1902-2000 (Box 5)
  - [1950], Pyle, Marjorie M. (Box 5)
    - The Good Fight - Contents, Chapter I, [1950] (Box 5)
    - The Good Fight - Chapter II, [1950] (Box 5)
    - The Good Fight - Chapter III, [1950] (Box 5)
    - The Good Fight - Chapter IV, [1950] (Box 5)
    - The Good Fight - Chapter V, [1950] (Box 5)
    - The Good Fight - Chapter VI, [1950] (Box 5)
    - The Good Fight - Chapter VII, [1950] (Box 5)
    - The Good Fight - Chapter VIII, [1950] (Box 5)
    - The Good Fight - Chapter IX, [1950] (Box 5)
    - The Good Fight - Chapter X, [1950] (Box 5)
    - The Good Fight - Chapter XI, [1950] (Box 5)
    - The Good Fight - Chapter XII, [1950] (Box 5)
    - The Good Fight - Chapter XIII, [1950] (Box 5)
    - The Good Fight - Chapter XIV, [1950] (Box 5)
    - The Good Fight - Chapter XV, [1950] (Box 5)
    - The Good Fight - Chapter XVI, [1950] (Box 5)
- Series V. Audiovisual materials, 1983-1994; 2 boxes, 1 lin. foot
  There are sixteen VHS videotapes in this series, most of them of Hinshaw testifying as an expert witness. Others are informational tapes dealing with tuberculosis, leprosy, or asbestos. There is also one ninety-minute cassette tape of reminiscences. This series is separated from the main collection and housed with the audiovisual materials. It is arranged chronologically.
  - Asbestos - NOVA Jedi, 1 March 1983, 10 December 1983 (Othertype Rec. 271)
  - San Diego Asbestos Litigation, 3-4 December 1984; 4 tapes (Othertype Rec. 271)
    "Deposition of Dr. Hinshaw"
  - Asbestos - CBS (2 in 1), 17 October 1985 (Othertype Rec. 271)
  - HCH Deposition - Asbestos (Salt Lake City, Utah), 1985; 3 tapes (Othertype Rec. 271)
  - Dr. Henshaw (sic) Deposition (Knoxville, Tennessee), 10-12 July 1986; 4 tapes (Othertype Rec. 271)
  - Leprosy, 23 June 1987 (Othertype Rec. 271)
  - MCH, 4 July 1989 (Othertype Rec. 271)
  - Tuberculosis: The Enduring Enemy - American Thoracic Society, 23 May 1994 (Othertype Rec. 271)
  - Audiotape to Dr. Ryan, n.d. (Othertype Rec. 271)